{
  "reference_number": "12052",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "2050 is too late. 2040 at the very least"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Short lived gases, essentially agricultural methane are up to 100 times more potent than C02 Over 8-10 years that's a lot of warming."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "see 2 in other comments below"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Not fast enough and there needs to be some way of ensuring the budgets are met"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "All budgets should be changeable as further scientific data is available"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The CCC should play a considerably larger part in decision making. See 7 & 8 in other comments below"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "ETSs are financial tools that do little other than allow those with money to buy their way in to continuing to emit greenhouse gases.\nActual reduction is necessary."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "See 6 in other comments below"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Something has to."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Do you mean that organisations wouldn't voluntarily share information? If so then yes."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Zero Carbon Bill Submission First of all I'd like to point out that compared with many other, if not all, \"developed\" countries, it is dead\neasy for NZ to reach zero carbon. It has but 4million people, a temperate, relatively amenable (for the time being) climate, an\n\nelectricity sector 80% or so renewable, a population not averse to bucking the trend (nuclear free) and a new government, for the\ntime being, that has shown itself willing to tackle climate change. Unfortunately it also has a fiscally responsible, essentially neoliberal\ngovernment, an economy dependant on exports and international trade, an agricultural and transport sector that is dependant on\n\nCO2 emitting fossil fuels and a society that in the last 40 years or so has shown one of the greatest increases in disparity between\nthe rich and the poor in the \"developed\" world. So there's a fair bit for a Zero Carbon Act or more pertinently, the Climate Commission,\n\nto deal with. But it's a good start and I support the idea. With the following caveats, conditions and considerations. 1. 2050 is too late.\n2040 is marginal. 2030, if not earlier is necessary to meet the Paris agreement's optimistic, 1.5C warming target. Surely NZ signed up\n\nto this? Albeit on a voluntary basis? 2. Essentially emissions have to be reduced, not offset. Yes, planting trees is essential but short\nterm havestable commercial forestry is not the answer and carbon credits are nothing but a trendy, acceptable form of colonisation;\n\nexport of the problem to a less fortunate part of the world. If not financial skullduggery. 3. Reduction of emissions means that we have\nto change our economy and lifestyle. Sorry you electric car owners but one flight to Auckland for a conference or a Big Day Out\nundoes all the savings from a year of Leaf commuting. The Zero Carbon Act/Climate Commission must not start by assuming that we\n\ncan maintain our \"standard\" of living while reducing our emissions. 4. But at the same time, it must ensure that our poorer citizens are\nlooked after. There's a lot of carbon emissions our well off, dare I say, middle class, citizens can forego poor things and stay alive and\n\nbugger all those living in the likes of South Dunedin on nigh on zero hour contracts and the benefit pittance can. Social Justice I think\nit's called, if you want an acceptable term rather than ill health and early death. 5. Zero carbon by 20** requires serious consideration\n\nof the re-localisation of the economy. Local food, local industry. Reduction of reliance on international trade, transport, multinational\ncorporations, financial dealings. The reversal of the neoliberal agenda of the past 50 years has to be on the agenda. 6. So who is\ngoing to be on the Climate Commission? The body that steers NZ to Zero Carbon? Our major export earners? Fonterra - methane,\n\ncoal? Tourism -aviation fuel? Federated farmers - methane, diesel? Ex National Party politicians? This is not a forum for excusing the\nstatus quo but one for coming up with the answers. Quickly. Necessary are: climate scientists to remind us of and update the\n\nproblem. economists (for want of a better word) to provide alternatives to the present neoliberal hegemony and the doers, those\nwho are already part of the solution, those who have demonstrated a competence in sustainable energy, local food, electric transport\n\netc. (Not lobby groups). We want a direct path to the future for our children and the world, not one littered with hurdles and ditches\nconstructed by those with vested interests in the status quo. 7. So what power/influence should the Climate Commission have over\n\nGovernment? It is after all an unelected body. Perhaps here we should consider the role of the (unelected) Treasury and M.B.I. on\ngovernment policy? The treasury has unquestionably had a role in the neoliberal stance of government and MBI has been touring the\ncountry of late promoting the old and new Trans Pacific Trade Partnership with scant regard for its relevance to the Paris agreement..\n\nConsiderable power has been quietly given to or assumed by these bodies over public policy. So why not the Climate Commission?\nThere's a precedent and the impending consequences are somewhat dire. Should the politicians in government be obliged to\n\naccept and implement the Commission's recommendations or will it be voluntary and will they only do so if they are of the climate\ncrisis rather than climate denier persuasion or can get some electoral advantage? 8. As a pinko leftie, all too aware of the dangers of\n\ndictators yet with any remnant belief in democracy compromised by US elections, I'm wary of placing policy decisions in the hands of\nanyone, let alone a few appointees. However, if the Commission is so constituted as to come up with informed, well reasoned\nrecommendations based on the latest science and research, then I think it has to have considerably more status than an advisory\n\nbody. Informed opinions are our best hope."
    }
  ]
}
